<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The morality of the seventh-day-Sabbath disproved in answer to C.T. Tillam's book, entituled, A present from prison, dedicated to L.C. Hobson ... / written by the learned J.B., Master of arts, at the request of the said L.C. Hobson.</title>
            <author>J. B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 54 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A26814</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B113</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32844</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12773119</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12773119</idno>
            <idno type="VID">93687</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A26814)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 93687)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1029:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The morality of the seventh-day-Sabbath disproved in answer to C.T. Tillam's book, entituled, A present from prison, dedicated to L.C. Hobson ... / written by the learned J.B., Master of arts, at the request of the said L.C. Hobson.</title>
                  <author>J. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Francis Clark for L. Curtis,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tillam, C. T. --  A present from prison.</term>
               <term>Sabbath.</term>
               <term>Sunday.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:93687:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE MORALITY OF THE Seventh-day-Sabbath Diſproved.</p>
            <p>IN ANSWER To <hi>C. T. Tillam</hi>'s Book, Entituled, <hi>A Preſent from Priſon,</hi> Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to <hi>L. C. Hobſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>WHEREIN</hi> The moſt Material Points in another Book, Entituled, <hi>A Diſcourſe of the Sabbath,</hi> lately Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by <hi>Henry Sowrsby</hi> and <hi>Mehetabel Smith,</hi> are ſuccinctly diſcuſs'd.</p>
            <p>Written by the Learned <hi>J. B.</hi> Maſter of Arts, at the Requeſt of the ſaid <hi>L. C. Hobſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Col. 2.16, 17.</hi>
               </bibl> Let no man therefore judge you in Meat, or in Drink, or in Reſpect of an Holy-day, or of the New Moon, or of the Sabbaths, which are a ſhadow of things to come, but the Body is of Chriſt.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Francis Clark</hi> for <hi>L. Curtis.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:93687:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:93687:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Morality of the Seventh-day-Sabbath Diſproved, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Page" n="1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 1. THE word <hi>Moral,</hi> according to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon uſage, is all one as to ſay <hi>Natural,</hi> and is oppoſed to that which is <hi>Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nial,</hi> or <hi>Poſitive,</hi> or of <hi>meer Inſtitution.</hi> This being ſo, (as you cannot be ignorant of) I wonder you ſhould talk of removing the Veil of Obſcurity lying upon the word Moral, unleſs it were, that wanting a ſolid Anſwer, you had a Mind to Quibble upon words; for you know that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and other Philoſophers have written Books concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Moral</hi> Duties, by which I believe you your ſelf will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, can be underſtood no other than thoſe Duties that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Reaſon exacteth of all Men, as they are Men.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Page" n="2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 2. In that you here barely ſay, that the main thing in Queſtion is undeniable; namely, <hi>That the Seventh day Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath is as Naturally Holy, as the ſix days are Naturally Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</hi> This to me ſeemeth plainly to Argue, that you had nothing material to alledge to prove your Aſſertion. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways you know well enough that I, and almoſt all other Chriſtians whatſoever deny it: Yea, I for my part, had brought many (as I believe) convincing Reaſons, to ſhew that I have good ground for the denyal thereof. Neither doth it follow, that <hi>becauſe God in the production of Natural things did not act unnaturally; neither was the Inſtitution of the Seventh-day-Sabbath contrary to his Natural intention;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Law of Nature doth require of all Men to obſerve the Sabbath: For to omit your own affirmation, that God <hi>inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted</hi> the Sabbath, which plainly ſheweth it not to be <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral,</hi> and ſo <hi>Moral</hi> but <hi>Poſitive;</hi> I might by the ſame Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Argue, that for as much as God did not act unnaturally
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:93687:3"/>
in producing the Tree of the Knowledge of Good and Evil; neither was it contrary to his Natural inclination to forbid the eating of the ſame; therefore it was a <hi>Moral</hi> and <hi>Natural</hi> Duty to abſtain from it, which I think you your ſelf will deny. If you do not, certain I am, that as you will ſcarce find any man that will Second you, ſo will it be altogether impoſſible for you to ſhew, that Natural Reaſon (ſetting aſide the Commandments of God) did dictate unto <hi>Adam,</hi> that he ought to forbear the eating of that Tree above all the other Trees of the Garden. Or why (if it be a <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Moral</hi> Duty) the ſame Tree is not ſet forth to us by God, that we may ſhew our Obedience by abſtaining from it. Theſe Expreſſions of yours, that God did Celebrate and Obſerve the Seventh day Sabbath are unſound, there being no ſuch thing affirmed of God in the Scripture, but only of Men, ſee <hi>Levit.</hi> 23.32. <hi>From Even to Even ſhall you Celebrate your Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath.</hi> And <hi>Exod.</hi> 31.16. <hi>The Children of</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſhall keep the Sabbath to obſerve the Sabbath throughout their Generations.</hi> For to <hi>Celebrate and Obſerve,</hi> ſuch or ſuch a time, argueth that it hath been Commanded by ſome other. Moreover when God is ſaid to have Sanctified or <hi>Hallowed</hi> the Sabbath, it was not that <hi>he himſelf,</hi> but that <hi>Men</hi> ſhould obſerve and keep it holy, as appeareth by the Fourth Commandment.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Page" n="3"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 3. Your Compariſon between a Wife in Relation to her Husband, and the Sabbath in Relation to a Chriſtian, doth not hold. For Marriage, though in the beginning in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted of God, is yet not of inſtitution, but of Nature; the difference of Sects Naturally requiring it without ſuch an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution. And this (as I am told) is acknowledged by <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle</hi> the beſt Naturalliſt that ever was, who ſaith, <hi>Eth.</hi> 8. <hi>Chap.</hi> 12. That <hi>there is naturally Friendſhip betwixt Man and Woman, and that Man was Naturally made, rather for Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage than for Civil Society.</hi> But no ſuch thing as this can (I believe) be alledged out of <hi>Ariſtole</hi> concerning the Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Sabbath.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Page" n="4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 4. That other Similitude of yours between the Sun and the Sabbath, being wholly of your own making, without any hint of the Scripture, is altogether frivolous, and proveth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:93687:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
nothing. And whereas you Adviſe me to ceaſe Polluting of the Sabbath, in as much as I have (ſay you) acknowledged the Seventh-day-Sabbath to be Holy by Divine Inſtitution. I wonder you ſhould ſo boldly impoſe on me, when you know ſufficiently, even by this very writing of mine, which you endeavour to anſwer, that I deny the Seventh-day-Sabbath now to be Holy, believing it, as being a ſhaddow, to be done away by Chriſt. Neither doth that Paſſage, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4.9. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate the contrary. For when that Divine Author ſaith, <hi>there remaineth therefore a reſt,</hi> (ſo I am told the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is rightly rendred, as will appear by two paſſages of the Septuagint, <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.30. <hi>Lev.</hi> 23.32. where the word is ſo uſed) <hi>to the People of God,</hi> he meaneth not the <hi>reſt</hi> of the Seventh-day-Sabbath, but the <hi>reſt</hi> of the Kingdom of Heaven, or (as the Author ſtileth it, Verſe the 10.) <hi>the reſt of God, into which whoſoever is entred, he alſo hath ceaſed from his own works, as God did from his.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to ceaſe from our own works, as God did from his, is to ceaſe from them, as never to return again to them; not to ceaſe for one day, and then to Labour again as before. Again, this reſt is inferred from thoſe words, <hi>verſe.</hi> 6. and ſo are meant of ſuch a <hi>reſt,</hi> into which the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did not enter becauſe of Unbelief. But <hi>Moſes</hi> teſtifieth that they kept the Reſt of the Seventh-day-Sabbath, <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.30. Moreover, this is a Reſt into which we ſhould labour to enter; but there needeth no labouring to reſt on the Seventh-day-Sabbath. Finally, when it is here ſaid, <hi>there remaineth a Reſt,</hi> this plainly implyed that the Reſt here ſpoken of, is ſomething that is reſerved for the People of God, and ſo not enjoyed at preſent, and therefore not the Reſt of the Seventh-day-Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath. Thus much appeareth from the ſame word thus uſed in the 6th. Verſe foregoing.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Page" n="6"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 6. Your ſaying, <hi>That the Seventh day is every way Moral, both by Natural Production, and by Primitive Inſtitution,</hi> ſheweth plainly, that you are miſtaken in the true Notion of <hi>Moral,</hi> and my uſe of the ſame. For I (as appeareth by my words, which you cite, <hi>page</hi> 1.) diſtinguiſh that which is <hi>Moral</hi> from that which is of <hi>Inſtitution,</hi> eſteeming that to be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:93687:4"/>
               <hi>Moral,</hi> which the light of Nature dictateth, that it ought to be, or at leaſt may laudably be done, though God had not Inſtituted and enjoyned the ſame; which if you can make good, concerning the Obſervation of the Seventh-day-Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, then will I readily aſſent to you that it is <hi>Moral.</hi>
            </p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Page" n="7"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 7. Where did you learn, that the work of <hi>the Law, written in mens Natural hearts, is the Old Covenant?</hi> For, doth not the Scripture oppoſe the New Covenant to that Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant which God made with the Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> when he brought them out of <hi>Egypt, Heb.</hi> 8.8, 9, 10. And doth not the Author of that Epiſtle, in the 13th. Verſe affirm, That <hi>in as much as he ſaith, a new Covenant, he hath made the firſt old?</hi> So that it undeniably follows, That the firſt Covenant which God made with the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> when he brought them out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> is the Old Covenant. It is alſo as evident, that the words of the Law is that Old Covenant, there being no other Old Covenant, but the Law delivered in Writing by <hi>Moſes.</hi> Again, where did you learn, That <hi>the words of the Law, written in the Chriſtians hearts, is the new Covenant?</hi> 'Tis true indeed that the Scriptures ſaith, the New Covenant conſiſteth in this, That <hi>God will write his Laws in his peoples hearts,</hi> but doth not affirm, that he will write <hi>the words of the Law</hi> (whereby <hi>Moſes</hi> Law is uſually alone underſtood in the Scripture) on their Hearts: So that by <hi>the laws</hi> which God promiſeth to write on the Hearts of his People, muſt needs be underſtood, not the <hi>laws</hi> which he had formerly delivered by <hi>Moſes,</hi> the Mediator of the Old Covenant, but thoſe which he would afterwards deliver by Chriſt, the Mediator of the New Covenant. Whereby you may perceive, that the New Covenant differs from the Old in the very <hi>laws</hi> that were written, as well as in the Tables whereon they were written, (theſe being Tables of the Heart, the other Tables of ſtone) and alſo in the Inſtrument of writing them, (theſe being written by the Spirit of the Living God, the other with Ink) 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3. So that your Error in diſtinguſhing (as you did) the Old Covenant from the New, is conſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. As for thoſe words then, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.15. <hi>by the works of the law,</hi> is meant the works of <hi>Moſes</hi> Law (for of that it is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:93687:4"/>
treated in the fore-going words) and conſequently the <hi>word</hi> or <hi>matter,</hi> or <hi>things</hi> (for theſe Expreſſions amount to the ſame) of <hi>Moſes</hi> Law, written in the Hearts of the <hi>Gentiles;</hi> not the things that are therein, meerly of Inſtitution, and ſo Ceremonial or Poſitive, (for none can know ſuch things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they be told him) but only thoſe that be Natural and Moral. For that ſuch things of the Law were written in the Hearts of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> appeareth every where by their writings, and for the breach of them they are reproved in the Scripture, as the <hi>Tyrrians</hi> are blamed for not keeping Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, <hi>Amos</hi> 1.9. The <hi>Edomites</hi> for Cruelty, <hi>ibid. ver.</hi> 11. The <hi>Ammorites,</hi> for inſulting over other mens Calamities, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 25.3. But no where ſhall you find, that the Heathens are Rebuked in Scripture for not keeping the Sabbath; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any hint in their Writings, that they thought themſelves bound to ſuch a Duty. Wherefore it is manifeſt, that the keeping of the Sabbath is no <hi>Moral</hi> Duty, which the Light of Nature doth dictate unto men, that they ought to perform. But you will, perhaps, demand of me, how the Condition of Chriſtians excelleth that of Heathens and Jews, if the work of the Law was written in the Hearts of the one, as <hi>Paul</hi> teſtifieth, and the word of the Law was in the Heart of the other, as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.14. <hi>The word is nigh thee, in thy Mouth, and in thy Heart, that thou mayeſt do it.</hi> I Anſwer, that the difference lyeth chiefly in two things: Firſt, the things of the law are not ſaid to be written in the Hearts either of Jews or Heathens, by the Spirit of the living God, (and ſo not ſo plainly and ſo eaſily Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible to them) the contrary whereof is affirmed of Chriſtians. Secondly, their Hearts are not ſaid to be Hearts of Fleſh, but on the contrary, the Jews hearts are called hearts of ſtone, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 11.19. which may be as truly affirmed of the Heathens hearts; whereas the hearts of Chriſtians are by <hi>Paul</hi> termed Hearts of Fleſh, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.3.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Page" n="9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 9. You are here, as well as in other paſſages of your Book, ſomewhat injurious to me, in impoſing that upon me, which I neither ſaid nor meant. For did I give this as a ground for us to forget the Seventh-day-Sabbath, becauſe God
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:93687:5"/>
hath Commanded us to remember it? Yea, do I not again and again tell you, that God hath no where Commanded us Chriſtians to remember any ſuch Sabbath?</p>
            <p>What can I with Reaſon conclude from hence, but that you had a mind to render me Contemptible in the eyes of the Brethren, by aſcribing ſo Ridiculous a kind of Reaſoning to me? As little ingenious is your Reprehenſion of me, a little after, ſaying, that I am miſtaken, in denying that to be Naturally Moral which depends upon Memory, where you leave out the words, <hi>as to know,</hi> as you do in ſundry other Paſſages afterwards, which expreſſion quite varieth the Caſe. For certainly that which a man cannot know but by means of his memory, is ſuch a thing as is not Naturally written in his heart, but ſuggeſted to him from without. Neither doth the greatneſs and goodneſs of God depend upon memory, <hi>as to know,</hi> which words you again leave out, dealing as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfully as before. For it is Naturally imprinted in the Heart of every man, that God is good and great, but not that we ought to keep the Seventh-day-Sabbath, as will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to any man that is acquainted with the Writings of ſuch as are meerly Naturaliſts.</p>
            <p>The Goſpel, as to the principle Myſteries therefore, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendeth the Natural Underſtanding of man to find out: For ſo the Apoſtle intimateth, when he ſaith, <hi>We preach the things that neither Eye hath ſeen, nor Ear hath heard, neither hath it come up into the Heart of man.</hi> Wherefore no man was bound to know, or publiſh theſe things without Divine Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation and Command. And conſequently they are not <hi>Naturally Moral;</hi> that being <hi>Naturally Moral,</hi> which is taught by the Light of Nature.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Page" n="12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 12. 'Tis true, a Child can of himſelf no more know who are his Parents, than he can which is the Seventh day. But prove that it is as much written in the Nature and Heart of man, that he ſhould Celebrate the Seventh day, when he is told which day of the Week is it, as that he ſhould honour his Parents, when he hath once learned who are they. Were this ſo, the Heathen, who are very ſtudious of the Law of Nature, and have left us Excellent Treatiſes concerning the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:93687:5"/>
ſame, would as well have delivered Precepts about the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Sabbath, as they do about Honouring our Parents.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Pag." n="13"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 13. When I affirm, that the Sabbath was a ſign of Gods Sanctifying his own People, you would (had you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the finding out of the Truth, and not abuſing both of your ſelf and others with a vain ſhew) eaſily have per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the Text cited by me out of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> for the Proof thereof, that I meant it in relation to Gods People, under the Old Covenant, and not under the New.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Pag." n="14"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 14. You deny that ever the Sabbath did ſtoop to any Law, either Ceremonial or Moral, becauſe (ſay you) this and other Moral Laws have evermore ſubmitted to the Will and Pleaſure of the Royal Law-giver. How doth this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove my Argument, unleſs you do withal ſhew, that the Law-giver never willed the Precept of the Sabbath to be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, that other Precepts might be kept? The contrary where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is very evident from the Texts of Scripture that I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged in my third Reaſon; alſo from <hi>Numb.</hi> 28.9. where certain Sacrifices are enjoyned by God, to be Offered on the Sabbath day, which could not be done without the breach of the Fourth Commandment of the Decalogue, where all manner of Work is forbidden on that day. Accordingly, the Prieſts on the Sabbath-day did in the Temple Profane the Sabbath, and were blameleſs, as Chriſt ſpeaketh, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.5. Here you ſee plainly that the Law of the Sabbath is broken, and that by the Will of God, that the Law of Sacrifices might be kept. But you ſhall never find in the Scripture, that the Law concerning Mercy, Righteouſneſs, Faith, or any other undoubted Moral Duty, is ever Profaned, that the Sabbath might be kept. For when you alledge on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that the Moral Law, which ſaith, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteal, or Covet,</hi> doth ſtoop as low as that of the Sabbath, and for Proof thereof, cite <hi>Exod.</hi> 11.2. you are miſtaken, for the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites</hi> are there Commanded by God, neither to <hi>Steal,</hi> nor to <hi>Covet,</hi> but only (as I am told the inſpection of the <hi>Hebrew</hi> words will inform you) to ask of the <hi>Egyptians</hi> Veſſels of Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and Veſſels of Gold. But to ask ſomething of another,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:93687:6"/>
was never yet counted to be a breach of either the Eighth or Tenth Commandment of the Decalogue. Neither is that Moral Law, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill,</hi> violated; or as you term it, proſtituted by that Command of God, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22.12. For as much as the killing forbidden in the ſixth Commandment, is by God himſelf, <hi>Exod.</hi> 21.12, 14. explained to be coming upon a man preſumptuouſly, and ſlaying him with guile; neither of which can be ſaid of <hi>Abraham</hi>'s attempt to ſlay his Son, he having received an expreſs Commandment from God to do it. Neither was that Moral ſentence of acquitting the Innocent, and condemning the Wicked, ſubjected, and as it were, ſubverted (ſo you are pleaſed to ſpeak) in the Death of Chriſt; for the <hi>Jews</hi> that Condemned and killed Chriſt, are by God in the Scripture pronounced to have done it by Wicked hands, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.23. and they accordingly exhorted to Repent, that they might receive the Remiſſion of their ſins, <hi>ver.</hi> 38. Which Juſtification is not contrary to thoſe words of the Law, <hi>I will not Juſtifie the Wicked, Exod.</hi> 23.7. Which are meant of ſuch a Juſtification, whereby the Wicked Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is Approved and Vindicated, and not whereby he is For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given upon his Repentance, and turning from his Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
            <p>You ſhould have done rightly to prove, and not barely aſſert, that Natures Law never allowed a man to have more Wives than one: For though I freely grant, that the Law of Nature doth dictate it to be better for a man to content him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with one Wife, yet doth it not ſuggeſt that the contrary is ſinful, howbeit the Law of Chriſt hath now made it ſo. And a wonder it is to ſee what pains many men take (but without ſucceſs) to prove that Polygamy is contrary to the Law of Nature. You ſhould likewiſe have proved, that the Act of <hi>Hoſea</hi> the Prophet, in Marrying one that had been an Harlot, was againſt the Law either of God or Nature, and not have taken it for granted.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Pag." n="16"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 16. When the Diſciples of Chriſt did pull the Ears of Corn on the Sabbath-day, and eat them, rubing them with their Hands, they did (as the <hi>Phariſees</hi> objected to them) what was not Lawful to do on the Sabbath. For though the Law
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:93687:6"/>
allowed a man to pull Ears of Corn in another mans Field, <hi>Deut.</hi> 23.25. yet might not this be done on the Sabbath, as being a breach of the Fourth Commandment. This that I have ſaid is further confirmed by our Saviours Anſwer to the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> wherein are ſo many notable Conſiderations, clearly evincing the Ceremoniality of the Sabbath, that this one Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory is abundantly ſufficient to determine the Queſtion in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate between us. For firſt, our Saviour defendeth the breach of the Sabbath in his Diſciples, by the Act of <hi>David,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hungry, brake the Ceremonial Law of God, in eating the Shew-bread, which none but the Prieſts were allowed to eat. But ſhould our Saviour have defended the breach of a <hi>Moral</hi> Law, by the breach of a <hi>Ceremonial</hi> one, who would not preſently have diſcerned the diſparity? Secondly, he Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth it by the deed of the Prieſts, who Offering Sacrifices in the Temple on the Sabbath, did Profane the ſame, and yet were blameleſs. Where he intimateth that the Temple was more Sacred than the Sabbath, becauſe in that place the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath was Profaned without blame. Thirdly, he Argueth that the Diſciples did well in breaking the Sabbath upon ſo ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent an Occaſion, becauſe God deſired Mercy and not Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: Where by Mercy he meaneth all Moral Duties, among which Mercy is eminent; as by Sacrifices he underſtandeth all Ceremonial and poſitive Duties, in as much as Sacrifice is chief among ſuch performances. That this is the right meaning of the words, and not that Fancy of yours touching the Sacrifice of the Sabbath, appeareth by the uſe of them to the ſame pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.13. For when the <hi>Phariſees</hi> blamed our Saviour for eating with Publicans and Sinners, Chriſt, in defence of himſelf, biddeth them go and learn what that is, <hi>I will have Mercy and not Sacrifice:</hi> Thereby intimating that to abſtain from ſuch Company, was to be reckoned amongſt Sacrifice and Ceremonial things; but to be Familiar with them of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to Convert them, was a work of Mercy, and ſo might be upon Occaſion obſerved with the breach of the other. This being ſo perſpicuous, how is it that you ſhould ſay, That <hi>till now you never met with any that charged our Saviour with putting upon the Sabbath the Tittle of Sacrifice;</hi> ſince it is apparent by the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:93687:7"/>
Diſcourſe and Practice of all Chriſtians in general through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole World, that they eſteem the Obſervation of the Seventh-day-Sabbath to be Ceremonial, and ſo fitly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed by our Saviour, under the appellation of Sacrifice. Again, how is it, that to deceive the ſimple, you ſhould caſt forth ſo many empty Expoſtulations, and talk of my cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring Chriſt himſelf as Ceremonial? To which purpoſe you alledge (though very impertinently) theſe words, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.12. <hi>But this man, after he had offered one Sacrifice for ſins.</hi> And whereas it is evident, that the word Sacrifice in the fore-cited paſſage of <hi>Hoſea,</hi> is meant of the Ceremonial Sacrifice of the Law, amongſt which the Sacrifice of Chriſt ought not to be reckoned; for after God had ſaid, <hi>I deſired Mercy, and not Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice,</hi> he preſently addeth, <hi>and the knowledge of God more than Burnt Offerings.</hi> By which it appeareth that by Sacrifice he meaneth ſuch Sacrifice as was joyned with Burnt Offerings, according to the preſcript of the Law, to which <hi>Jer. Chap.</hi> 7.21. alluding, ſaith, <hi>Put your Burnt Offerings to your Sacrifices and eat Fleſh.</hi> I ſhould take little Comfort in diſcovering theſe ſhameful miſtakes of yours, were it not that I ſaw you went about to Rob us of our Chriſtian Liberty, and to bring us into Bondage unto the weak and Beggarly Rudiments of the World. Fourthly, our Saviour Warrants the violation of the Sabbath in his Diſciples, becauſe <hi>the Sabbath was made for man, and not man for the Sabbath,</hi> and therefore ought to yield to the Neceſſities of man. Which thing alſo ſheweth that the Sabbath is <hi>Ceremonial.</hi> For as for <hi>Moral</hi> Duties, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture teſtifieth that man was made for them. Thus <hi>Acts</hi> 17.26, 27. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, that <hi>God made mankind to ſeek the Lord,</hi> which all will confeſs to be a <hi>Moral</hi> Duty. And <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.10. <hi>We are his making</hi> (ſo I am told the <hi>Greek</hi> word ſignifieth) <hi>Created in Chriſt Jeſus unto good Works, which God hath before prepared, that we ſhould walk in them.</hi> But the good Works enjoyned in the Goſpel, are by all confeſſed to be <hi>Moral,</hi> and not <hi>Ceremonial</hi> Performances.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, It is ſaid, that <hi>for as much as the Sabbath was made for Man, and not Man for the Sabbath, therefore the Son of Man is Lord even of the Sabbath.</hi> Which words imply, that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:93687:7"/>
the Son of Man could, in caſe of Mans Neceſſity, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence with the Law of the Sabbath, other ways how was he Lord of it? For doth not his being Lord of it, ſignifie that he was above it, and had Power over it? But no where is it ſaid or intimated in the Scripture, that the Son of Man, yea, any other, is Lord of <hi>Moral</hi> Duties, they being in their own Nature indiſpenſable, in that they agree to Man, as he is a Rational and Sociable Creature, and ſo bound to Act Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionably and ſociably. Neither did you ever Read that ſuch Duties have in Scripture been by Chriſt diſpenſed with: Wherefore thoſe Expreſſions of yours, which you ſo often inculcate in your Book, <hi>That the Sabbath is made for Man, and that Chriſt is Lord of the Sabbath,</hi> do (being rightly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood) ſubvert your Opinion, intimating that the Sabbath is Ceremonial, and may Lawfully upon an emergent Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of Man be diſpenſed with. That the Walls of <hi>Jericho</hi> were ſurrounded for ſeven days together, and conſequently on the Sabbath is evident. But that the ſeventh day of the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounding was the Sabbath, appeareth not out of the Text. For to evince that, you muſt ſhew that they began to ſurround the City on the firſt day of the Week, whereas no ſuch thing is ſo much as hinted in the Sacred Text. Wherefore that which you infer from thence, touching the extraordinary Dignity that was put upon the Sabbath, in that the City was taken Miraculouſly upon that day, is altogether groundleſs. Howbeit, this is certain from the ſtory, (as I before hinted) that the Sabbath was broken, in as much as to Compaſs a City in a Hoſtile manner on that day, is to Profane it, by Working upon it, contrary to the Fourth Commandment.</p>
            <p>So that this plainly ſheweth the Obſervation of the Sabbath to be no <hi>Moral</hi> Duty, as being diſpenſed with. What you farther ſay of <hi>Jericho's being a Type of</hi> Babylon, <hi>and of the man of ſin's changing the Times,</hi> are more groundleſs ſurmiſes, than what you before ſpake concerning the taking of <hi>Jericho</hi> on the Sabbath day, as would eaſily appear, if you attempted to confirm thoſe Notions of yours by the Scripture rightly and ſoundly Interpreted.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:93687:8"/>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Pag." n="20"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 20. Here you confeſs as much as I deſire, namely, <hi>That the Inſtitution of the Sabbath cometh only from the power and authority of God.</hi> For this unanſwerably proves it to be <hi>Ceremonial;</hi> the difference between a <hi>Moral</hi> and <hi>Ceremonial</hi> Law lying in this, that the one is Naturally written in the Heart of Man, and ſo ought to be Obſerved, though God had not Commanded it; (whence the Heathens, to whom God had not made known himſelf, nor given any Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments and Judgments, are nevertheleſs grievouſly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended by the Prophets for not Obſerving <hi>Moral</hi> Duties; See <hi>pag.</hi> 7. fore-going.) Whereas Ceremonial Laws depend meerly upon the Will and Authority of God Commanding them. Where I admire that you ſhould Reprove me for ſuggeſting <hi>That the Sabbath receives Being, and takes Riſe from a Reaſon without us.</hi> For is not the Power, Will, and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of God, upon which only you your ſelf ground the Obſervation of the Sabbath ſomething without us?</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Pag." n="21"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 21. How irrational therefore are your words, where (contradicting your ſelf) you ſay, <hi>'Tis unſeemly to aſſert, that the Ceremonial Laws did ever riſe from any Reaſon without us, for even their ſpring-head was Originally from the Pleaſure and Providence of God?</hi> For is not the Pleaſure of God a Reaſon without us? And are not ſuch Laws as flow from the Pleaſure of the Law-giver meer <hi>Placits,</hi> and ſo <hi>Poſitive</hi> and <hi>Ceremonial</hi> things? For inſtance, the ſacrificing of Beaſts, was it not a thing that ſprang from the Pleaſure of God? And is it not therefore <hi>Ceremonial,</hi> there being no other Obligation upon Men to perform it, but the Command of God? ſo that the injunction of God about that matter now ceaſing, we are no longer bound thereunto. 'Tis true, that <hi>Moral</hi> Precepts are ſometimes in the Law inforced by reaſon from without, as Obedience to God, from deliverance out of <hi>Egypt;</hi> but then theſe Precepts do not Originally ſpring from ſuch Reaſons, but from the Law of Nature, to which thoſe other Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations are added, and conſequently Men have a new Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to ſuch Duties, which they were before bound by Nature to perform.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:93687:8"/>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 24. To prove that the ſabbath is not <hi>Moral,</hi> I alledged that it is called a <hi>Sign,</hi> and a <hi>Covenent.</hi> The Adverſary wanting a ſolid Anſwer hereunto, and intending here, as he doth <hi>pag.</hi> 16. to make a Flouriſh, ſaith, that I may as well prove our Saviour himſelf to be a Ceremony, for as much as the ſame Titles are given to him; though the Paſſages that he citeth, reach not home to his purpoſe (as will eaſily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to him that ſhall confer them with thoſe concerning the Sabbath.) Yet I willing joyn Iſſue with him, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that in as much as Chriſt is called a Sign and a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, it doth unavoidably follow, that the Myſtery of Chriſt is ſuch a thing as dependeth not on the Law and light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; but only on the good pleaſure of God, as Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf intimateth, <hi>John</hi> 6.40. <hi>This is the will of him that ſent me; that whoſoever beholdeth the Son, and believed on him, ſhould have Eternal Life.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> Eph. 1.5. ſaith plainly, <hi>Having predetinated us unto the adoption of Children through Jeſus Chriſt unto himſelf, according to the good pleaſure of his will.</hi> Neither will it be poſſible to prove that by the light of Nature (ſetting aſide the Commandment of God) we are directed to believe in Chriſt, and expect Salvation from him. So that I retort the Adverſaires ſimilitude upon him, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude firmly from thence, that as the Myſtery of Chriſt is not Moral, but dependeth on the good Pleaſure of God, ſo neither is the obſervation of the Sabbath which he compareth therewith.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Pag." n="25"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 25. In this Page the Adverſary ſpeaketh out, and ſheweth, that though he often mentions the Name of Chriſt, and Chriſtians, yet his deſign is, by this Doctrine of the Seventh-day-Sabbath, to bring us from Chriſt unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> for he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly ſaith, <hi>I know no newer Covenant than the Covenant of Life and Peace, which was made with Levi,</hi> Mal. 2.5. For is not Gods Covenant with Chriſt Jeſus newer than his Covenant with <hi>Levi?</hi> Or is not his Covenant with <hi>Levi,</hi> that which he made by the hand of <hi>Moſes</hi> the <hi>Levite,</hi> when <hi>Iſrael</hi> came out of <hi>Egypt?</hi> Why is Chriſt called <hi>the Mediator of a better Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> and thereby oppoſed to the <hi>Levitical</hi> Prieſts, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.21, 22. If there be no newer Covenant of Life and Peace, than that which of Old was made with <hi>Levi?</hi> Behold there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:93687:9"/>
O ye Brethren that love the Lord Jeſus and his Goſpel, how the Adverſary here doth caſt off his Vizard, acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no new Covenant to be made with Chriſt, but that the old Covenant with <hi>Levi</hi> is ſtill in force. For if this be ſo, why do we not preſently renounce the Goſpel, and take upon us the Obſervance of the Law, which was received under the <hi>Leviti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal</hi> Prieſthood? Why do we not trun <hi>Jews?</hi> For you ſee this is the Mark, at which the Adverſary, notwithſtanding his ſpecious Pretences to the contrary, doth indeed aim.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Pag." n="27"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 27. That none before <hi>Moſes</hi> time was under Reproof, either from their own Conſcience, or from God (that we Read of) for breaking the Sabbath, is an evident Proof, that the Sabbath is not <hi>Moral;</hi> elſe why ſhould they not have been Reproved for the breach of that as well as of other Duties, which are confeſſedly Moral? Neither is it to the matter to ſay as you do, that the Sabbath was in force before <hi>Moſes,</hi> unleſs you prove it to be therefore in force, becauſe the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture did ſuggeſt it unto Men, which you have not yet, nor ever ſhall be able to evince. If you thereupon demand, how it could be, that God ſhould have Commanded it from the beginning, and yet the Patriarchs not be blamed for neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it? I Anſwer, becauſe it was grown out of knowledge, as that paſſage, <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.14. ſheweth, where it is ſaid, <hi>Thou madeſt known unto them thy Holy Sabbath.</hi> But none can be juſtly reproved for not obſerving a <hi>Ceremonial</hi> and <hi>Poſitive</hi> Law, when it is once grown out of knowledge and forgotten; and this is the Reaſon, why the word <hi>Remember</hi> is prefixed to this, and to no other of the Ten Commandments; implying that the Sabbath, being of Inſtitution, and no part of the Law of Nature, as the other Nine Commandments are, might in after Ages, as well as it had formerly, be utterly forgotten <hi>Page</hi> 34. Though the word Sabbath be not mentioned <hi>Exod.</hi> 16.4, 5. yet is the thing it ſelf there plainly intimated, when God ſaith, <hi>On the ſixth day they ſhall prepare what they bring in, and it ſhall be twice as much as they gathered daily.</hi> For why ſhould that which they brought in on the ſixth day be prepared and be double to what they gathered daily, but becauſe they might not prepare or gather any <hi>Manna</hi> on the Seventh day, but
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:93687:9"/>
ought to keep it for a Sabbath of Reſt? So that it is truly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by <hi>Moſes, ver.</hi> 23. that the Lord had ſaid, <hi>to morrow is the Reſt of the Holy Sabbath,</hi> in that he had before Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to gather on the ſixth day twice as much as they did upon any other day, and alſo to prepare it. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is undeniable that God Commanded the Sabbath in the fourth and fifth Verſe of the ſixteeth Chapter of <hi>Exodus.</hi>
            </p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Pag." n="40"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 40. That Text, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.16, 17. is ſo directly oppoſite to the Adverſaries Opinion, and ſhineth with ſo full a Light, that it is no marvel that he ſhould ſtrive might and main to raiſe up a whole Cloud of Duſt to obſcure it; but all in vain, ſeeing he may ſooner darken the Sun it ſelf. For firſt, when the Apoſtle here ſaith, <hi>Let no man judge you in meat or drink,</hi> doth he not thereby ſignifie, that the difference of meats and drinks formerly enjoyned by God, doth now ceaſe? Secondly, when he addeth, <hi>or in reſpect</hi> (ſo I am told) ought the words to be rendred, as will appear by comparing 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.10. and Chap. 9.3. (where the ſame expreſſion is ſo uſed) <hi>of an Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day</hi> (or <hi>Feaſt) or New Moon, or Sabbath:</hi> Doth not this in like manner ſhew, that neither the <hi>Feaſts</hi> or <hi>New Moons</hi> formerly Commanded to the People of God, do more bind Chriſtians than the difference of meats and drinks aforeſaid. But if they be not obliged to obſerve them, they are by the ſame Reaſon as little bound to keep the Sabbath; which is here put in the ſame Rank with <hi>Feaſts</hi> and <hi>New Moons:</hi> Neither can it be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed that by the Sabbath is here meant the Seventh-day-Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath. For there is no place in all the New Teſtament where the word Sabbath (in <hi>Greek</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) doth ſignifie any other than the Seventh-day-Sabbath. Yea, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſimply put (ſo that it is not ſaid, <hi>ſuch or ſuch a time ſhall be to you a Sabbath,</hi> or <hi>to the Land</hi>) it doth always in the Old Teſtament denote the Seventh-day-Sabbath. Again, the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath is here diſtinguiſhed from <hi>Feaſts</hi> and <hi>New Moons,</hi> and therefore can be underſtood of no other than the Seventh-day-Sabbath. For though, as you Object, the word <hi>Feaſts, when put by it ſelf,</hi> may comprehend the Seventh-day-Sabbath (as perhaps it doth, <hi>Lev.</hi> 23.23.) yet when it is joyned with <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths,</hi> it cannot do ſo (for then the ſame thing would be
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:93687:10"/>
twice expreſſed) and this is manifeſt from that Text, <hi>Lev.</hi> 23.37, 38. <hi>Theſe are the Feaſts of the Lord, which you ſhall Proclaim to be Holy Convocations, beſides the Sabbaths of the Lord.</hi> As for other <hi>Sabbaths</hi> beſides the Seventh-day-Sabbath, they are comprehended under the word <hi>Feaſts:</hi> So that in the foreſaid paſſage, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.16. by <hi>Sabbath</hi> joyned with <hi>Feaſts</hi> and <hi>New Moons,</hi> can no other <hi>Sabbath</hi> be poſſibly meant but the <hi>Seventh-day-Sabbath,</hi> as thoſe inſtances which in my former Diſcourſe I alledged out of the Old Teſtament do clearly prove, neither ſhall ſo much as one inſtance be alledged out of the New to the contrary. And whereas you further Object (though as little to the purpoſe as before) that we ſhall find one <hi>Sabbath</hi> ſo far from being a <hi>Feaſt,</hi> that it is the day of ſevere Affliction. Have I not here juſt cauſe again to tax you for Quibbling up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on words, ſeeing it is apparent from the 4th. Verſe of this 23d. of <hi>Levit.</hi> that by <hi>Feaſts</hi> are not meant <hi>times of Belly-cheer,</hi> but <hi>Holy Convocations,</hi> wherein men ceaſed from their ordinary Labour, and were employed in Religious Duties, whether they made Mirth, or Afflicted their Souls? In the third place (to return to the fore-cited Text, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.16, 17.) Where the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſuper-addeth, <hi>which are a ſhadow of things to come, but the Body is of Chriſt.</hi> This hath relation to rhe five things men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in the 16th. Verſe, at leaſt to that which is immediately fore-going the <hi>Sabbath.</hi> So that the <hi>Sabbath</hi> (diſtinguiſhed from <hi>Feaſts</hi> and <hi>New Moons,</hi> and ſo according to the perpetual uſage of the Scriptures, ſignifying no other than the <hi>Seventh-day-Sabbath</hi>) is by the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> called <hi>a ſhadow,</hi> the Body whereof is exhibited to us in Chriſt, namely, in the Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Sabbath of the Kingdom of Heaven. Wherefore to bring us back to ſhadows, after that the Body is come, is not only Prepoſterous, but tendeth to the enſlaving us under the Rudiments of the World, and inſtead of Sons to make us Servants.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Pag." n="57"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 57. For as much as the Adverſary, not only here, but elſewhere in his Book ſaith, that Chriſt delivered the Law to <hi>Iſrael</hi> at Mount <hi>Sinai.</hi> I would fain hear from him why the Scriptures, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.6. and 12.24. calleth Jeſus the Mediator of a <hi>New</hi> and <hi>better Covenant?</hi> For certainly this implyeth, that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:93687:10"/>
ſome other Perſon was the Mediator of the Old and woſe <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</hi> Again, why doth the Apoſtle <hi>John</hi> prefer Chriſt before <hi>Moſes</hi> in this regard, namely, that <hi>whereas the Law was given by</hi> Moſes, <hi>Grace and Truth came by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Chap. 1.17. Undoubtedly this ſtrongly Argueth that the Law was not given by Chriſt; wherefore you deal ridiculouſly, in deſiring me to take heed of perſwading others to tranſgreſs any one word that Chriſt immediately Commanded at Mount <hi>Sinai.</hi> To what purpoſe do you beſtow ſuch Elegies upon the Law of God?</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Pag." n="61"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 61. Is it not to inſinuate into the Minds of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wary Readers, that I am a Contemner, yea, an Oppoſet thereof? Whereas I think very Honourably of it, as being Holy, Juſt, and Good: Only I believe (what you your ſelf dare not diſavow) that all the <hi>Ceremonial</hi> and <hi>Shadowy</hi> things thereof are now done away in Chriſt. And that the Sabbath is one of thoſe <hi>Ceremonial</hi> and <hi>Shadowy things,</hi> I have unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyably evinced, as from other paſſages of the Scripture, ſo eſpecially from that Text of <hi>Paul, Col.</hi> 2.16, 17. which plainly ſignifieth, that as the difference of Meats, and Drinks, and the Celebration of Feaſts and New Moons, ſo alſo the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Sabbath was <hi>a ſhadow</hi> of things to come, the Body whereof is now held forth unto us in Chriſt.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Pag." n="68"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 68. As for that paſſage, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.21. where our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Chriſt bids his Diſciples pray, <hi>that their flight might not be on the Sabbath day,</hi> the words plainly intimate, that it would be Lawful to flee on that day (and conſequently that the Law concerning the Sabbath would ceaſe, whereby it was enjoyned, <hi>that no man ſhould remove out of his place on the ſeventh day,</hi> Exod. 16.29.) The words (I ſay) plainly intimate, that it would be Lawful to flee upon that day, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways why ſhould they pray, that their flight might not be then? Nevertheleſs it would not be expedient, in that the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing <hi>Jews,</hi> thinking the Sabbath ſtill to remain, would be ready to offer Violence to ſuch as ſhould attempt to fly on that day. Yea, perhaps the believing <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves, not underſtanding their own Liberty in Chriſt, but thinking the Sabbath ſtill in force, would be exceedingly grieved, if
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:93687:11"/>
they ſhould be reduced to a Neceſſity either of Periſhing, or of Flying on the Sabbath day. Of which thing I will ſpeak more anon. If you Reply, that Chriſt calleth it the Sabbath in relation to the time that ſhould be long after his death; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as I believe that by his death the difference of times, in point of Holineſs, and conſequently the Obſervation of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> was aboliſhed, according to the Doctrine of <hi>Paul, Col.</hi> 2.14. I An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that the Scripture calls the times of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Feaſts, after the death of Chriſt, by the ſame names they had formerly. See <hi>Acts</hi> 12.3. and Chap. 20.16. when notwithſtanding you your ſelf will not deny, that the Obligation to obſerve thoſe Feaſts, had then ceaſed.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Pag." n="69"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 69. What needed the mention of the firſt day of the Week, commonly called Sunday, when I never affirmed, that Chriſt hath left us any Precept for the Obſervation of the ſame. Howbeit, we have the Practice of all believing <hi>Gentiles,</hi> down from the Apoſtles unto our time, who have unanimouſly and conſtantly obſerved the ſame, as being that day, which is in <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. called the <hi>Lords day;</hi> which perpetual Cuſtom of Chriſtians is ſufficient to Warrant our keeping of the <hi>Lords day:</hi> Whereas no ſuch thing can be alledged to juſtifie the obſerving of the Seventh-day-Sabbath. And therefore when you ſay, <hi>that Chriſt hath eſtabliſhed in his Houſe all the Moral Duties of</hi> Moſes <hi>Houſe,</hi> it is nothing to the purpoſe, unleſs you firſt prove, that the keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Sabbath is a Moral Duty, the contrary whereof, my compariſon taken out of the Scripture, doth evince. For Chriſt being as Faithful in the Houſe of God as <hi>Moſes.</hi> If it had been his Will that his Diſciples ſhould have obſerved the Seventh-day-Sabbath, he would have expreſly enjoyned it, and not have left them to gather it by I know not what uncertain Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences, ſuch as you, and others of your Opinion make uſe of. For <hi>Moſes</hi> openly and frequently Commanded to the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> that they ſhould keep the Seventh-day-Sabbath. So that your proceeding herein is juſt like the dealing of the Papiſt about the Popes pretended Supremacy. For when it is Queſtioned whether he be the Judge of all emergent Controvercys amongſt Chriſtians, the Papiſt having no ſuch Precept from Chriſt in the Scripture, where Chriſt Ordaineth the Pope or Biſhop of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:93687:11"/>
               <hi>Rome</hi> to ſuch Judicature, bring inſtead thereof certain far-fetch'd probabilities and conſequences to prove it. In like manner you when you are urged by me and other Chriſtians to ſhew where Chriſt (who was as faithful in the Houſe of God as <hi>Moſes</hi>) hath Commanded his followers to keep the Sabbath, alledge Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances for other things, and ſimilitudes, and ſtrains of your own Poetry, and other like impertinences, without producing ſo much as one undoubted Precept for the ſame. But whereas you ſay, that Chriſt hath confirmed all the <hi>Moral</hi> Precepts of <hi>Moſes:</hi> Who denies it? You ſhould have done well, not to have begged the thing in Queſtion, but to have proved that the Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the Sabbath is a <hi>Moral</hi> Duty. But this you have not yet been, nor ever ſhall be able to perform.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Pag." n="79"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 79. That <hi>Paul</hi> excluded the Law touching the Seventh-day-Sabbath out of the Counſel of God towards believing <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles,</hi> is evident, both from his perpetual ſilence in his Writings touching ſuch matters (the contrary whereof you being unable to prove, do here, as well as elſewhere turn aſide to impertinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies) and alſo by his ranking the Sabbath among ſhadows, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.16, 17. for the not obſerving of which, no man ought (as you, not regarding his Injunction, raſhly do) to Judge and Cenſure others as Offenders.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Pag." n="80"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 80. I wonder at your boldneſs to aver, <hi>That the Apoſtles did own the Sabbaths Obſervation, as a great vertue, and admoniſh Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to beware of the breach thereof as a moſt provoking ſin;</hi> and that this is evident from <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.9. where it is ſaid, <hi>Whoſoever therefore ſhall break one of the leaſt of theſe Commandments, and teach men ſo, ſhall be called leaſt in the Kingdom of Heaven.</hi> Is here (or in the whole Chapter) ſo much as one word of the Sabbaths; yea doth not this expreſſion, <hi>the leaſt of theſe Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments,</hi> argue that he ſpake of his own Commandments, differing from thoſe in the Law? For ſhould you underſtand it of the Commandments in the Law, would it not from thence unavoidably follow, that Chriſtians are bound to keep all the Law of <hi>Moſes;</hi> even to the leaſt Commandment thereof; So that of Chriſtians we muſt all preſently turn Jews. And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this be not indeed the bottom of your deſign, you give me too much reaſon to ſuſpect, as by other expreſſions of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:93687:12"/>
yours, ſo eſpecially by that down-right Jewiſh Speech of yours, <hi>p.</hi> 25. where you ſay that you know no newer Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, than the Covenant of Life and Peace that was made with <hi>Levy.</hi> As for that other Text, from whence you endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to prove, <hi>That the Apoſtles did own the Sabbath obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as a great vertue,</hi> namely <hi>Luke</hi> 23.56. where it is ſaid, <hi>They reſted on the Sabbath, according to the Commandment?</hi> Is here any mention made of the Apoſtles, or of their owning the obſervation of the Sabbath, after the death of Chriſt? Is not that which is here ſpoken of the <hi>Commandment,</hi> meant of the <hi>Commandment</hi> in the Law? which the godly Jewiſh Women here ſpoken of, knew not to be aboliſhed; as neither did the believing Jews in general a long time after, as you may ſee, <hi>Acts</hi> 21.20. where the Apoſtle <hi>James</hi> ſaith to <hi>Paul, Thou ſeeſt, Brother, how many thouſands of Jews there are that believe, and they are all Zealous of the Law.</hi> But as for any Commandment of Chriſt about the Sabbath, you do not alledge any ſuch out of the Goſpel (there being none) but inſtead thereof bring uncertain Conſequences.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Pag." n="83"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 83. In this Page your Judaiſm again breaks forth, and plainly diſcovereth it ſelf, when you tell us, <hi>that</hi> Moſes <hi>Writings were then</hi> (namely, when that Decree, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.28, 29. was made) <hi>eſteemed the moſt Righteous Rule for true Believers.</hi> Which words of yours are directly oppoſite both to the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of the Apoſtle, ſet down in the foreſaid Chapter (where they blame ſuch as taught the Diſciples that they ought to keep the Law) as alſo to the words of Chriſt himſelf, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20. <hi>Teaching them to obſerve</hi> not <hi>whatſoever</hi> Moſes, but <hi>whatſoever Chriſt had commanded them.</hi> Yea, your words make the Law more Righteous than the Goſpel; for if the Law be the <hi>moſt Righteous</hi> Rule for Believers, there is no other Rule <hi>ſo Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> as it, and conſequently the Rule of the Goſpel muſt ſtoop to the Law. By this may eaſily be perceived what the tendency of your Doctrine is, and how by thoſe goodly words of <hi>Gods Sanctifying Preſence on the Sabbath day,</hi> and the like, you go about to beguile the ſimple.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="Pag." n="84"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 84. This laſt Argument alledged by me out of <hi>Rom.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.2, 3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is like to that other, drawn from <hi>Col.</hi> 2.16, 17. and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:93687:12"/>
it doth ſo fully and exactly determine the buſineſs touching the Ceremoniality of the Seventh-day-Sabbath, that it is a wonder how any man profeſſing himſelf a Chriſtian, and to own the Authority of the New Teſtament, ſhould make any ſcruple of this matter. And you your ſelf ſufficiently ſhew by your many turnings and windings in putting off this Portion of Scripture, that you could by no means abide the force there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. For when it is ſaid, <hi>ver.</hi> 2. <hi>One man believes he may eat all things, another being weak, eats herbs.</hi> Doth not this clearly imply, that the difference of Meats formerly obſerved accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the will of God, whether before or after the Law, doth now ceaſe? For that there was diſtinction between clean and unclean Beaſts and Fowls, before the Law; and that by the approbation of the Lord God himſelf, is apparent from <hi>Gen.</hi> 28.20. Alſo that by <hi>clean</hi> Beaſts and Fowls, are meant ſuch as may Lawfully be eaten; by <hi>unclean,</hi> ſuch as may not, is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from <hi>Lev.</hi> 11.3, 4, 46, 47. So that if your Exception con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning days, were true, namely, that the fifth Verſe meant of ſuch days only as were Ordained to be kept Holy under the Law, and not of the Sabbath, which was Inſtituted before the Law; I might by the ſame Reaſon ſay as much of Meats, namely, that the Apoſtle meaneth ſuch a difference of Meats as was introduced by the Law: ſo that ſtill thoſe Meats remain unclean to us Chriſtians, which were by God himſelf called unclean before the Law, and they (it is likely) were as many if not the very ſame with thoſe under the Law. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by this kind of Arguing we are not ſure of having at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained any Liberty in this kind by means of Chriſt. You may by this ſee how abſurd your exceptions are, &amp; that as the difference of Meats, whether in Relation to the Will of God before or after the Law, is now taken away; ſo in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner the difference of days, and therefore that none is by the Commandment of God to be now eſteemed more Holy than another. For the Apoſtle plainly affirmeth (without reprehending it) <hi>that one man eſteemeth every day alike, and that he which eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not one day above another eſteemeth it not unto the Lord.</hi> But you have yet another exception, and that more ſtrange than the former, for you ſay, that by <hi>every day the Apoſtle only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:93687:13"/>
every one of the ſix daies, becauſe,</hi> Exod. 16.4. <hi>(which is the firſt place where this expreſſion occurreth) when the Lord ſaith, the people ſhall go out togather a certain rate every day, there is meant every one of the ſix daies.</hi> But I pray you tell me why, when you cited this place out of <hi>Exodus</hi> you would not take ſo much pains to conſult the Hebrew Text, you having skill in that Language? Or, if that ſeemed too painful, why you did not caſt you eye upon what the Tranſlators ſet in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent? For they there tell you, that the words in Hebrew are, <hi>the portion of a day in its day, which being ſo, your exception, that by every day,</hi> Rom. 14.5. is meant <hi>only every one of the ſix daies of the Week,</hi> hath not ſo much as any colourable warrant from the aforeſaid Text in <hi>Exodus;</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently as your Exception was but a meer evaſion to my Argument, drawn from the aforeſaid Text of the Apoſtle it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains invincible, namely, that not only the difference of Meats, but alſo the difference of daies, is, (as to any Law of God) now taken away, and accordingly they are but weak and ill informed Believers, who think the Obligation of the Seventh-day-Sabbath doth ſtill remain.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
